Hello everyone. Today we present "The Power of Physics Eyes: Interference Fringes" - from soap bubbles' rainbows, we can see atoms, earthquakes, and gravity.
みなさんこんにちは 今回はシャボン玉の虹から原子も地震も重力も見える
A video with this somewhat mysterious title that explores the amazing power of interference fringes.
物理の目 干渉縞のすごい力というちょっと不思議なタイトルの動画をお届けします
Now everyone, you've blown soap bubbles before, right?
さてみなさん シャボン玉って吹いたことありますよね
Those beautiful rainbow-colored patterns that shimmer - actually, using exactly the same principle, we can see invisible atomic arrangements and ground movements from earthquakes.
あの虹色に輝く美しい模様 実はあれと全く同じ原理で目に見えない原子の並び方や地震による地面の動き
And even gravitational waves coming from space.
さらには宇宙からやってくる重力波まで見ることができるんです
Today we'll introduce you to this mysterious world of interference fringes.
今回はその不思議な干渉縞の世界をご紹介します
Let's start with a phenomenon called Newton's rings.
まずはニュートンリングという現象から始めましょう
Some of you might have seen this in science class experiments.
これ理科の実験で見たことある人もいるかもしれません
When you place a flat convex lens on a glass plate,
平らな凸レンズをガラス板の上に置くと
beautiful concentric ring patterns appear spreading from the center.
中心から広がる同心円状の美しい縞模様が現れます
These are Newton's rings.
これがニュートーニングです
Why do such patterns form?
なぜこんな模様ができるかというと
Light reflects in the thin air layer between the lens and glass.
レンズとガラスの間にある薄い空気の層で光が反射しているんです
Light reflected from the upper surface and light reflected from the lower surface overlap,
上の面で反射した光と下の面で反射した光が重なり合って
causing a phenomenon called interference.
干渉という現象を起こしているんですね
What's interesting here is why they form beautiful concentric circles.
ここで面白いのがなぜきれいな同心円になるかということ
Actually, the air layer thickness d has this relationship with the distance r from the center.
実は空気層の厚さdは中心からの距離rとこんな関係があるんです
The air layer thickness equals the radius squared divided by twice the lens's radius of curvature.
空気層の厚さは半径の2乗をレンズの曲率半径の2倍で割った値になります
In other words, the farther from the center, the thicker the air layer becomes.
つまり中心から離れるほど空気層が厚くなっていく
This change in thickness creates the beautiful concentric patterns.
この厚さの変化が同心円状の美しい模様を作り出すんです
Why do bright and dark regions form?
なんで明るい部分と暗い部分ができるのか
This is due to the wave nature of light.
これは光の波の性質によるものです
When the optical path difference - the difference in distance traveled by two light rays -
光路差つまり2つの光が進む距離の差が
equals exactly an integer multiple of the light's wavelength,
光の波長のちょうど整数倍になると
the waves reinforce each other and become bright.
波が強めあって明るくなります
Conversely, at positions offset by half a wavelength,
逆に波長の半分ずれた位置では
the waves cancel each other out and become dark.
波が打ち消しあって暗くなるんです
Imagine waves in a pool.
プールの波を想像してみてください
If two waves perfectly overlap,
2つの波がぴったり重なれば
they create a large wave. If peaks and troughs overlap, they flatten out.
大きな波に山と谷が重なれば平らになる
It's the same principle.
それと同じです
Now here's the really amazing part.
さてここからが本当にすごいところ
The ring radius is about 5mm or so - easily measurable with a ruler, right?
リングの半径は5ミリとか定規で簡単に測れる大きさですよね
But what about the air layer thickness?
でも空気層の厚さはどうでしょう
Let's actually calculate it.
実際に計算してみると
For example, if the ring radius is 5mm
例えばリング半径が5ミリ
and the lens radius of curvature is 1 meter,
レンズの曲率半径が1メートルの場合
the air layer thickness is about 12.5 micrometers!
空気層の厚さはなんと約12.5マイクロメートル
That's about one-fifth the thickness of a human hair.
これ髪の毛の太さの5分の1くらいです
So from visible 5mm fringe patterns,
つまり目で見える5ミリの縞模様から
we can determine invisible 12.5 micrometer
目には見えない12.5マイクロメートルという
ultra-fine thicknesses!
超微細な厚さが分かっちゃうんです
This is the magic of interference fringes.
これが干渉縞の魔法
It's nature's amplification device that shows us invisible things magnified hundreds to thousands of times.
見えないものを数百倍から千倍に拡大して見せてくれる
And soap bubble rainbows work on exactly the same principle.
自然の増幅装置なんです
However, the difference from Newton's rings is
そしてシャボン玉の虹色も全く同じ原理です
that the medium changes from air to a thin soap film,
ただしニュートンリングとの違いは
and the shape becomes irregular patterns instead of concentric circles.
媒質が空気から石鹸水の薄い膜に変わって
The soap bubble film thickness varies by location.
形も同心円じゃなくて不規則な模様になること
And depending on the film thickness, places where 700nm red light reinforces
シャボン玉の膜の厚さは場所によって違います
differ from places where 450nm blue light reinforces,
そして膜の厚さによって波長700nmの赤い光が強み合う場所と
which is why those beautiful rainbow colors appear.
波長450nmの青い光が強み合う場所が違うから
Now here's the main topic.
あの綺麗な虹色が現れるんです
In 1912, a scientist named Max von Laue
さてここからが本題
discovered that X-rays diffract when directed at crystals.
1912年マックス・フォン・ラウエという科学者が
What's amazing about this is
X線を結晶に当てると回折することを発見しました
that it was the moment humanity first became able to see atomic arrangements.
これ何がすごいかというと
In X-ray diffraction, Bragg's law becomes important.
人類が初めて原子の並び方を見ることができるようになった瞬間なんです
It sounds complicated, but the principle is simple.
X線回折ではブラックの法則っていうのが重要になります
Atoms in crystals are arranged regularly,
難しそうに聞こえるけど原理はシンプルです
and when the path difference of X-rays reflected from each layer
結晶の中の原子は規則正しく並んでいて
equals an integer multiple of the wavelength,
各層で反射されたX線の高度差が波長の整数倍になったとき
the X-rays reinforce each other.
X線同士が強め合うんです
Same principle as soap bubbles.
シャボン玉と同じ原理ですね
In actual measurements, we first record diffraction patterns
実際の測定ではまず解説パターンを記録して
and investigate at which angles X-rays become strong.
どの角度でX線が強くなるかを調べます
Then using Bragg's equation, we calculate interatomic distances
そしてブラックの式を使って原子間の距離を計算し
and ultimately reveal how atoms are arranged -
最終的に原子がどう並んでいるか
their three-dimensional structure.
3次元の構造を明らかにするんです
X-ray diffraction is actually used in many places.
X線回折って実はいろんなところで使われてます
New material development, geological surveys,
新しい材料の開発、地質調査
and interestingly,
そして面白いところでは
in art authentication too - analyzing pigment components
美術品の鑑定にも顔料の成分を分析して
to distinguish authentic from fake
本物か偽物かを見分けたり
or estimate when paintings were created.
絵が描かれた年代の推定をしたりするんです
Next is InSAR. The formal name is Interferometric Synthetic Aperture Radar.
次はインサー。正式名称はInterferometric Synthetic Aperture Radar。
In Japanese, it's called synthetic aperture radar interferometry.
日本語で合成開口レーダー干渉法と言います。
This is a technology for measuring ground deformation from satellites.
これ、人工衛星から地面の変動を測る技術なんです。
The mechanism works like this:
仕組みはこんな感じです。
The satellite emits radio waves toward the ground and observes the same location again after some time.
衛星から地面に向けて電波を発射して、同じ場所を時間を空けてからもう一度観測します。
If the ground has moved due to earthquakes or other causes, the distance from the satellite changes, right?
もし地震とかで地面が動いていたら 衛星からの距離が変わりますよね
This distance change is detected as a phase difference between the two observation datasets.
この距離の変化を2回の観測データの位相差として検出するんです
During the 2016 Kumamoto earthquake, this technology played a major role.
2016年の熊本地震の時 この技術が大活躍しました
Amazingly, ground displacement of up to 1 meter - about the height of an adult's waist -
なんと最大で1メートル つまり大人の腰の高さくらいまで地面がずれたことが
was observed from space.
宇宙から観測されたんです
Rainbow-colored interference fringe patterns centered on the epicenter appeared on the ground surface like a giant soap bubble.
震源を中心とした虹色の干渉島パターンが、まるで巨大なシャボン玉みたいに地表に現れました。
What's amazing about this technology is that within hours of a disaster, we can understand damage conditions over a wide area.
この記述の何がすごいかって、災害が起きてから数時間で広い範囲の被害状況がわかることです。
We can check conditions in dangerous places where people can't enter, and by continuously observing the same location for years, we can capture slow changes like ground subsidence.
人が入れない危険な場所の様子も確認できるし、何年も同じ場所を観測し続けることで、地盤沈下みたいなゆっくりした変化も捉えられるんです。
Finally, the ultimate interference technology: gravitational wave detection.
最後は究極の干渉技術重力波検出です
Einstein predicted that when massive objects move, spacetime warps
アインシュタインが質量を持つ物体が動くと時空が歪んで
and this distortion propagates as waves.
その歪みが波として伝わるって予言したんですが
But they were too small - for nearly 100 years, no one could actually observe them.
あまりに小さすぎて100年近く誰も実際に観測することはできませんでした
Then on September 14, 2015,
そして2015年9月14日
the American research facility LIGO finally succeeded in detecting gravitational waves for the first time.
ついにアメリカの研究施設LIGOが重力波を初めて検出することに成功しました
They caught gravitational waves from black hole mergers that occurred 1.3 billion light-years away.
13億光年彼方で起きたブラックホールの合体による重力波をキャッチしたんです
It was 99 years after Einstein's prediction.
アインシュタインの予言から99年後の解除でした
LIGO is a massive L-shaped device with 4km arms, as shown in this aerial photograph.
LIGOはこの航空写真のように4kmもある巨大なL字型の装置です
Laser light is split into two arms and made to travel back and forth.
レーザーの光を2つのアームに分けて往復させます
When gravitational waves pass through, one arm stretches slightly while the other contracts.
重力波が通過すると片方のアームがほんのちょっと伸びてもう片方が縮む
This tiny change is detected using a Michelson interferometer.
このわずかな変化をマイケルソン干渉計で検出します
We're measuring incredibly small lengths,
ものすごく小さい長さを測っているのですが
but the measurement principle is actually very classical and orthodox.
測定のための原理は実はものすごく古典的でオーソドックスなものなんです
Here's the truly unbelievable part.
ここからが本当に信じられない話です
The detected displacement is only 10^-18 meters.
検出する変異はたったの10の-18乗メートル
That's incredibly small.
ものすごく小さいですね
To understand how small this is:
これがどれくらい小さいかというと
It's one-thousandth the size of a proton, the particle that makes up atomic nuclei.
原子核を作る粒子である陽子の大きさの千分の1
Comparing to the distance between Earth and the Sun,
地球と太陽の間の距離で例えると
it's the size of one hydrogen atom.
水素原子1個分の大きさ
If you expanded a hair's thickness to Earth's diameter,
髪の毛の太さを地球の直径まで拡大したとき
it would barely move 1 millimeter.
やっと1ミリ動くくらい
It's unimaginably small.
もう想像を絶する小ささです
But using the phenomenon of interference, we can measure this!
でも干渉という現象を使えばこれが測れちゃうんです
The first detected gravitational wave, called GW150914,
初めて検出されたGW1509-14という重力波は
was from a phenomenon where energy equivalent to 3 times the Sun's mass was released instantaneously.
太陽の質量の3倍分のエネルギーが一瞬で放出された現象でした
To detect displacements far smaller than protons,
陽子よりもはるかに小さい変異を検出するために
various noise countermeasures and interference amplification techniques are used,
様々なノイズ対策や干渉の増幅技術が使われていますが
but the fundamental principle is the classical Michelson interferometer -
根本的な原理は古典的なマイケルソン干渉系
the same light interference as soap bubble rainbows.
シャボン玉の虹と同じ光の干渉なんです
What all the technologies we've seen today have in common is interference fringes.
今回見てきた技術全部に共通しているのが干渉縞です
Path differences become phase differences, which appear as interference patterns.
高露差が位相差になってそれが干渉パターンとして現れる
Using this principle, we've visualized invisible things and amplified minute changes.
この原理で見えないものを見える化し微小な変化を増幅してきました
From the atomic world to global-scale changes,
原始の世界から地球規模の変動
and even spacetime waves coming from the far reaches of the universe -
そして宇宙の彼方からやってくる時空の波まで
we're observing everything using fundamentally the same principle as soap bubble rainbows.
すべてシャボン玉の虹と根本的には同じ原理で見ているんです
Interference fringes are truly a special eye given to physics.
干渉縞はまさに物理学に与えられた特別な目なんですね
How was that?
いかがでしたか?
Today we've journeyed together through the mysterious world of interference fringes.
今日は干渉縞の不思議な世界を一緒に旅してきました
The rainbow colors of soap bubbles we blew as children -
子供の頃に吹いたシャボン玉の虹色
using the same principle as those beautiful patterns,
あの美しい模様と同じ原理で
scientists can unravel atomic arrangements
科学者たちは原子の配列を解き明かし
and even capture gravitational waves from space.
宇宙からの重力波さえも捉えることができる
Doesn't this change how you see the world?
なんだか世界の見方が変わりませんか?
Next time you see soap bubbles, please stop for a moment and observe them.
次にシャボン玉を見かけたらちょっと立ち止まって観察してみてください
Keys to unlocking the universe's secrets might be hidden in those rainbow colors.
その虹色の中に宇宙の秘密を解き明かす鍵が隠れているかもしれません
Well then everyone, until the next video, farewell.
それでは皆さん、次回の動画までごきげんよう。